Samuel Kachuck

(818) 307 2685 • ☑ sbk83@cornell.edu • ❷ georei.com
 in skachuck • ⑤ skachuck

I am in the final year of a Ph.D. in geophysics at Cornell University. My interests include fluid dynamics and statistical physics in general, and glacial isostatic adjustment - how the earth responds viscoelastically to the mass redistributions of the last ice age, when over 4 million Gigatons of water moved from the oceans to the continents - in particular. My thesis research comprises the development and benchmarking of a tool for computing this response efficiently. It is the beginning of a comprehensive characterization of the errors in models of glacial isostasy and how these errors propagate to predictions of social importance, like land-water storage and sea-level changes.

Education

Cornell University Sep 2011 – Jun 2018 (expected)

Ph.D. in Geophysics

Cornell University Sep 2011 – Aug 2014

M.S. in Physics

Cambridge University, St. Edmund's College Oct 2010 – May 2011

M.A.St., in Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics

Wesleyan University Sep 2006 – June 2010

B.A. in Physics and Mathematical Economics

Research Experience

Graduate Research Fellow

May 2012 - Present

Cornell University

Advisor: Prof. Lawrence M. Cathles, III

Area: Glacial Isostatic Modeling and Analysis

o Computational study of the physics and errors in models of glacial isostatic adjustment.

Graduate Research Assistant

Sep 2011 - May 2012

Cornell University

Advisor: Prof. Itai Cohen

Area: Insect Flight Stability and Control

 Experimental study of the fluid dynamics and control mechanisms employed by Drosophilae to stabilize their flight against perturbations.

Research Assistant Oct 2010 – May 2011

GK Batchelor Fluids Laboratory *Advisor:* Dr. Stuart B. Dalziel

Area: Buoyancy in Permeable Media

• Experimental study of the various fluid dynamical regimes present when a buoyant plume flows past a permeable medium.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Aug 2008 - June 2010

Wesleyan University

Advisor: Prof. Greg A. Voth Area: Granular Gas Dynamics

• Experimental and computational study of the dynamics of 2D granular gases in gravity, both in steady state (when energy is continuously added) and in decay (when energy it is not).

Publications

- [1] **Kachuck, Samuel B.**, "Nondimensionalized relaxation method for efficient computation of time-domain viscoelastic love numbers," in prep.
- [2] **Kachuck, Samuel B.** and L. M. Cathles, "Constraining the geometry and volume of the barents sea ice sheet," *Journal of Quaternary Science*, in review.
- [3] Kachuck, Samuel B. and G. A. Voth, "Simulations of granular gravitational collapse," *Physical Review E*, vol. 88, no. 6, p. 062202, Dec. 2013, ISSN: 1539-3755. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevE.88.062202. [Online]. Available: http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.88.062202.
- [4] J. A. Perez, **Kachuck, Samuel B.**, and G. A. Voth, "Visualization of collisional substructure in granular shock waves," *Physical Review E*, vol. 78, no. 4, pp. 1–6, Oct. 2008, ISSN: 1539-3755. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevE.78.041309. [Online]. Available: http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.78.041309.

Teaching Experience

o Private Tutor (PHYS 2207, 2208, 1112, 2213, 2216; MAE 3780; CEE	3310), S2012 – present
o Analytical Mechanics (CU PHYS 3318), GTA	S2017
o Physics II: Electromagnetism (CU PHYS 2213), GTA	F2011, S2012, Su2012
o Physics I: Mechanics and Heat (CU PHYS 1112), GTA	F2012
o Quantum Mechanics I (W PHYS 214), UTA	S2010
o Mathematical Economics (W ECON 380), UTA	F2009
o General Physics II (W PHYS 116), UTA	S2009
o General Physics I (W PHYS 113), UTA	F2008
Chille	

Skills

Languages: Python, C/C++, FORTRAN, APL, LATEX, Matlab

Honors & Awards

o Douglas A Fitchen Scholar	2017
 AGU Outstanding Student Paper Award 	2016
 NSF GRFP Honorable Mention 	2012
o Phi Beta Kappa	2010
o Graham Prize	2010
o Karl van Dyke Prize	2010
 Plukas Teaching Apprentice Award 	2010
White Prize	2010
 Dean's List, Wesleyan University 	2006 - 2010
o Squire Fund Fellow	2007
o Chadbourne Prize	2007

All Publications

Google Scholar ID: nuMklOMAAAJ

Journal Articles.....

- [J1] **Kachuck, Samuel B.**, "Nondimensionalized relaxation method for efficient computation of time-domain viscoelastic love numbers," in prep.
- [J2] **Kachuck, Samuel B.** and L. M. Cathles, "Constraining the geometry and volume of the barents sea ice sheet," *Journal of Quaternary Science*, in review.
- [J3] Kachuck, Samuel B. and G. A. Voth, "Simulations of granular gravitational collapse," *Physical Review E*, vol. 88, no. 6, p. 062202, Dec. 2013, ISSN: 1539-3755. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevE.88.062202. [Online]. Available: http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.88.062202.
- [J4] J. A. Perez, Kachuck, Samuel B., and G. A. Voth, "Visualization of collisional substructure in granular shock waves," *Physical Review E*, vol. 78, no. 4, pp. 1–6, Oct. 2008, ISSN: 1539-3755. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevE.78.041309. [Online]. Available: http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/ PhysRevE.78.041309.

Oral Presentations.

- [O1] S. B. Kachuck and L. M. Cathles, "Nondimensionalized relaxation method for efficient computation of elastic love numbers," in *Workshop on Glacial Isostatic Adjustment and Elastic Deformation*, 2017.
- [O2] S. B. Kachuck, L. M. Cathles, A. Amantov, A. Hormes, and W. Fjeldskaar, "Emergence constraints on late weichselian barents sea ice sheet history," in *EGU*, 2014.
- [O3] S. B. Kachuck, "Velocity dependent energy loss in granular gravitational collapse," in *New York Condensed Matter Workshop*, 2011.

Posters.....

- [P1] S. B. Kachuck and L. M. Cathles, "Sloppy inversion and optimal experiment design for last glacial maximum barents sea ice sheet configuration," in *American Geosciences Union*, 2016.
- [P2] —, "Gia response suggests thick lithosphere under the appalachians," in *Institute for the Study of the Continents*, 2014.
- [P3] S. B. Kachuck, L. M. Cathles, A. Amantov, and W. Fjeldskaar, "North american peripheral bulge constraints on mantle rheology," in *European Geosciences Union*, 2014.
- [P4] L. M. Cathles, A. Amantov, S. B. Kachuck, and W. Fjeldskaar, "The seamod methodology of gia interpretation," in *European Geosciences Union*, 2014.
- [P5] S. B. Kachuck and L. M. Cathles, "Lithosphere, ice history, local emergence," in *European Geosciences Union*, 2013.
- [P6] S. B. Kachuck, "Granular gravitational collapse in realistically simulated granular gases," in 5th Annual Thesis Celebration, 2010.